Guide to the Bailey Willis Geological Formations Photographs
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Bailey Willis Geological formations photographs
1884-1899
A0099
Willis, Bailey, 1857-1949.
0.5 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer from the Dept. of Geology, 2000
Information about Access
None.
Biography
Bailey Willis, a member of the United States Geological Survey, came to Stanford University in 1915 to succeed John C. Branner as head of the Department of Geology and taught here until his retirement in 1922.
Scope and Content
This album contains photographs of various geological formations, including columnar basalt, monoclinal ridges and folds, sandstone dikes, and exfoliated granite. Locations include New Jersey, New York, West Virginia, California (Lassen, Inyo, and Shasta Counties), Colorado (Garden of the Gods and Golden), Nebraska (Sioux and Banner Counties), and South Dakota (Big Bad Lands and the Black Hills). Photographers and dates are identified on only a few images. In one image (taken in Wilbur, New York) an outdoor advertisement for a performance of Uncle Tom's Cabin is visible on a shed.
Collection Contents
- Pages 1-3: (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 41. Columnar basalt. O'Rourke's quarry, Orange Mountain, New Jersey
  - 67? The Shenandoah River near Harper's Ferry
  - 50. Middle quarry, Penryn Slate Company. Bedding of roofing slate coincident with cleavage
  - 48. Cliffs in Topmans Gulch, Jefferson County, New York
  - 57. Cherty layers interbedded with shales, eight miles below Quebec, Canada
  - 42. Columnar basalt. O'Rourke's quarry, Orange Mountain, New Jersey. North end of quarry
- Pages 4-6: (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 68? Potomac near Harper's Ferry. Note that the strata stand on end
  - 88. Monoclinal ridge. Colorado City, Colorado. Triassic and Jurassic
  - 140. Gravel spit near Mackinaw Island, Lake Michigan
  - 218. The cinder cone from the east, Lake Bidwell, Lassen County, California
  - 214. Sandstone dike penetrating Cretaceous shales, Dry Creek, California
  - 216. Lava field and cinder cone looking southwest across Lake Bidwell, Lassen County, California; Lassen Peak in the distance
- Pages 7-9: (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 45. Vertical columns of basalt with spheroidal parting and transverse structure. O'Rourke's quarry, Orange Mountain, New Jersey.
  - 43. Columnar basalt. South end of O'Rourke's quarry, Orange Mountain, New Jersey
  - 251. Overturned anticline in Massanutten beds, Panther Gap, Virginia; looking south
  - 401. Fault in the Gering formation half a mile north of Rutland siding, south of Crawford, Nebraska; looking west
  - 22. Anticlinal fold in Levis terrace, about Levis Station, Quebec, Canada
  - 23. Folding of shales and sandstone, south shore of the St. Lawrence River nine miles below Quebec
- Pages 10-12: (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 37. Brecciated limestone conglomerate. Highgate Falls, Vermont
  - 589. Folds in Cambrian sandstones and shales. Doe River, Tennessee
  - 27. Fold in Brown sandstone near Hancock, West Virginia
  - 26. Arched strata on Chesepeak [sic] and Ohio Canal near Hancock, West Virginia
  - 520. Protoceras sandstone area, Big Bad Lands, South Dakota, 1898
  - 525. the Pulpit, Big Bad Lands, South Dakota, 1898
- Pages 13-15: (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 441. Toadstool Park, northwest of Adelia, Sioux County, Nebraska
  - 327. Erosion by wind-blown sand; three miles northeast of Freeport, Banner County, Nebraska
  - 868. Plicated layers of thin bedded chert in limestone
  - 841. Lower Cambrian quartzite showing vertical cleavage in massive layers and interbedded thin layers without cleavage. Inyo County, California
  - 595. Concretions in the Laramie sandstone, Weston County, Wyoming
- Pages 16-18: (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 206. image missing
  - 209. Sandstone dikes cutting Cretaceous shales on Roaring River, Shasta County, California
  - 55. image missing
  - 145. Beach or bar joining Empire and Sleeping Bar bluffs on Lake Michigan
  - 176. Upturned lower shaley beds of the Helderberg formation at Wilbur, New York; looking north [large advertisement for performance of Uncle Tom's cabin visible on shed]
  - 157. Falls over Pentamerus and Tentaculite beds. South Bethlehem near Albany, New York; looking south
- Pages 19-21: (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 427. Sandstone columns of erosion. Garden of the Gods, Colorado, 1898
  - 223. Anticlinal fold in the Lewiston limestone and Monterey sandstone. North Fork of the Potomac River, two miles south of Hopeville, West Virginia; looking north
  - 210. Group of sandstone dikes on the North Fork of Cottonwood Creek, Shasta County, California
  - 47. Table Mountain near Golden, Colorado
  - 211. Group of sandstone dikes on the North Fork of Cottonwood Creek, Shasta County, California
  - 226. Near view of lava blocks on the edge of the lava fields near Lake Bidwell, Lassen County, California. The lava is basalt
- Pages 22-24: (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 430. Cathedral Spires. Garden of the Gods, Colorado
  - 434. Titanotheriun beds, two miles east of Adelia, Sioux County, Nebraska
  - 368. Toadstool Park, three miles northwest of Adelia, Sioux County, Nebraska. Thin sandstone layers in clays of Big Bad Lands series
  - 505. Pass over which Flour Trail crosses the Big Bad Lands. High level Pleistocene gravel in the foreground
  - 222. Anticline fold in the Lewiston limestone and Monterey sandstone, north fork of the Potomac River, two miles south of Hopeville, West Virginia; looking north
  - 254. Dakota sands in a pit just south of Bennett, Nebraska (note in pencil: "false bedding")
- Pages 25-27: (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 213. Sandstone dike penetrating Cretaceous shales, Dry Creek, California
  - 205. Sandstone dike penetrating Cretaceous shales. Dry Creek, Tehama County, California
  - 865. Plicated layers of thin bedded chert in limestone
  - 867. Plicated layers of thin bedded chert in limestone
  - 465. Granite Needles, near Harney's Peak, Black Hills, South Dakota, 1898
  - 469. The Needles. Southern Group, near Harney's Peak, Black Hills, South Dakota, 1898
- Pages 28-30: (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 35. Seams in limestone filled with calcite
  - 36. Seams in limestone filled with calcite
  - 507. Big Bad Lands north of Flour Trail, South Dakota
  - 519. Protoceras area, Big Bad Lands, South Dakota, 1898
  - 177. Cement rock and sand rock railroad cut one mile south of Whiteport Station, New York: looking north (note in pencil: "beds folded and eroded")
  - 182. Arch at High Falls, Ulster County, New York, looking northwest
- Pages 31-33: (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 87. Jurassic rocks. Como, Wyoming
  - 84. Triassic sandstone. Garden of the Gods, Colorado
  - 142. Spit on Train Island, Lake Superior
  - 242. Exfoliated granite dome in Tuolumne County, California
  - 121. Forest killed by drifting sand. Lake Michigan
  - 144. I recurved spit, duck Point, Grand Traverse Bay, Lake Michigan
- Pages 34-35: (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1189. Exfoliated granite, crest of the Sierra Nevada mountains (note in pencil: "no bedding")
  - 1198. Wind ripples on sand, Golden Gate Park, San Francisco
  - 1190. Wind ripples on sand, Golden Gate Park, San Francisco
  - 54. Boulders of decomposition formed by the decay of basalt. Table Mountain, Golden, Colorado, (note in pencil: "no bedding"), 1884
  - 1175. Potholes in the granite of the canon of the North Fork of the Mokelumne River, California
- Pages 36-37: (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 25. Section of anticlinal ridge near Dunkirk, New York. Devonian black shale
  - 128. Old lake shore near Pierrepoint, New York
  - 115. Shore of Lake Ontario, Pillar Point, New York. Typical glacial surface
  - 669. "Point Pots." Near Fountain Geyser in the Yellowstone National Park, 1899
  - 113. Striated limestone boulder from Norway, Iowa (half natural size)
- Original album covers (Box 2)